The first years of a young animal's life are the most crucial.
So, if they grow up without their mothers, these animals are going to need help.
Good morning!
Hello, darling.
We're going to meet baby animals whose only hope of survival lies with some very dedicated people...
What a clever girl.
..And find out what it takes to get them back into the wild.
This is about salvation for some little guys who've been through hell, who've been through trauma, who deserve a second chance.
'I'm biologist Patrick Aryee' and I'm in Central America, home to exotic and rare wildlife.
'Here, I'll be visiting centres where the wildlife 'gets incredible specialist care.'
That is remarkable!
'And I'm zoologist Lucy Cooke' and I'm in southern Africa, home to some of the most iconic animals in the world.
'I'll be helping out at rescue centres 'devoted to rehabilitation and release.'
You're going to become a wild cheetah one day, aren't you, if you carry on being this good.
'In this programme, I'll be meeting Manji, the baby rhino... '..who after a traumatic start to life 'now has to learn the skills he needs 'to return to the African savanna.'
Look at these guys!
They are ready to be wild rhinos.
'And I'll be helping Mandi, the orphaned tapir... '..discover her wilder side... '..so she can be reintroduced to her own kind.'
Oh, my God.
Mandi.
Join us as we follow these miracle orphans.
Through their most crucial moments.
On their long journeys back to the wild.
South Africa... ..home to some of the most loved and recognisable animals on the planet.
But pressures are mounting on the wildlife here and many species are now under threat.
None more high-profile than the African white rhino.
These extraordinary ancient beasts have roamed our earth for 50 million years but due to a recent surge in poaching, there are only 20,000 left in the wild.
Experts believe that they could completely disappear from the wild in the next five years, which means that every animal counts.
This is four-month old Manji...
There you go, my boy.
..An orphaned baby white rhino that lives here at Care For Wild Africa...
Oh!
It's a nice, wonderful morning.
Did you sleep well, my boy?
Did you sleep well?
..A rescue centre founded by Petronel Nieuwoudt.
She has over 20 years' experience working with wildlife and is surrogate mum to over 20 rhinos.
Hello, my girl, you're so big and so strong!
Look at that!
Petronel's rhinos are all at different stages of rehabilitation.
Some are large enough to roam free in a wild reserve... ..but rescued babies need care around the clock.
Happy baby!
And baby Manji is her biggest challenge yet.
'Manji means place of the stars.'
And he's a star, he's a star in my life.
He is the youngest rhino that Petronel has ever rescued.
OK, drips in first, drips in first.
At just two days old, his mother was killed by poachers for her horn... ..and he too was attacked with a machete, receiving near-fatal head injuries.
In every rescue, the first 48 hours are crucial.
Petronel didn't leave Manji's side.
He was so small and so skinny, the blood loss was immense and I called everyone I know.
I just know, "Hey, we're going to save this one."
And after intense medical treatment, doctors managed to save him.
Manji is the survivor of survivors, he's a brilliant little one.
I'm very, very proud of him and I love him, I love him to bits.
Manji now needs to learn how to be a wild rhino and Petronel is determined that he and all her orphans return to where they belong.
There was never a choice for me in looking after these giants.
It's a journey, it's a lifelong commitment.
I want them to be free, I want them to be in the wild.
On average, three rhinos a day are poached for their horns.
'Unsurprisingly, Petronel will take on any orphan that needs her help.
'The first stage of a rhino's rehabilitation is crucial 'and she wants to show me where their recovery begins.'
So, this is the intensive care unit?
Yeah.
This is where we have the babies, smaller babies or the animals that just came in after their rescue.
'In this intensive care unit, the most important thing 'is making sure orphans get the right nutrition.'
Hello!
Hello.
There we go!
'And nothing comes between a hungry rhino and its bottle.'
Hello, is that good?
So tiny!
Wow, they drank that so fast and that's just one of seven bottles that they drink every day.
But then these guys need to drink between 10 and 15% of their body weight every day, so it's a lot of milk.
White rhinos are highly social mammals and babies depend on their mothers for the first three years.
Come sit down.
There we go, there we go.
Having raised so many orphans, Petronel has a deep understanding of their emotions.
They are these giant, wonderful creatures and to build the trust with these guys is of utmost importance.
Really softly with a lot of emotion to make them feel safe, to make them feel that we look after their needs.
What's the most important part of the process of rehabilitation for Manji?
We want to release him back into the wild.
They are herd animals, they like to socialise and they play.
If I see him doing well in those stages, I know he will do well outside there.
In order to be a wild rhino, he's got to join the herd basically for survival?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
Absolutely so, yeah.
Over the next few weeks, Manji needs to learn how to fend for himself.
His whole world is about to change.
His next step is to leave this intensive care unit - the only place he's known for the last four months - and with these other orphans, move to a bigger space.
There, he'll practise the skills he'll need to prepare him for the wild.
Over 7,500 miles away is Costa Rica.
This meeting place of the Americas boasts a wealth of natural habitats.
It's a small country, a quarter of the size of the UK.
Bursting with wildlife, it's home to half a million species... ..making it one of the most biodiverse places on earth.
But with a growing human population, many of the extraordinary animals that live here are now under threat.
I'm on my way to a very special wildlife sanctuary on the Pacific coast of Costa Rica.
Now, it's in a really remote location and for good reason too, because the animals that it cares for are some of the most exotic and endangered in all of Central America.
I'm heading to the Macaw Sanctuary, run by Rodolfo Orozco Vega.
In his 15 years here, he's seen it expand and he now rescues and cares for many of Costa Rica's rarest animals, including majestic jaguars and these vocal characters.
What you can hear is the sound of great green macaws, what fabulous animals.
There are only 300 or so left in Costa Rica.
And they aren't the only endangered animals that he's protecting.
This is Mandi.
She's a Baird's tapir.
These herbivores are known to be shy and timid creatures.
Related to horses and rhinos, they're able to use their nose like a hand to pull leaves from branches and pick up food that's dropped to the ground.
So, Rodolfo, this is...
This is Mandi.
..The lovely Mandi.
Hello, Mandi.
This is the first time I've met a tapir.
There you go, Mandi.
She's lovely.
I love how she's just resting on me.
She seems very relaxed, very happy, content and quite tranquil.
And you can see from Mandi's face, whilst I'm feeding her, her eyes are completely closed.
'Mandi is an orphan.
'She was rescued from poachers at just four weeks old.'
'She was found tied up in a local village 'and was close to starvation.'
How big was she when she first came to the centre?
She was very little, very sick, sad and covered with scratches all over her body, even a scar in her neck because she was tied up by people.
So, the reason why she was so scarred and bruised was because of humans?
Yeah, exactly.
Humans were trying to eat Mandi, that simple.
Hunters killed the mother and they take the baby to their houses to, you know, to grow up and to eat it later.
'Tapirs are a protected species in Costa Rica 'but being hunted and eaten by humans 'is still one of the main threats they're facing.'
Don't you find it surprising that, considering there are only 5,000 of these tapirs left in the wild, that people are still hunting them?
Yeah, it is really surprising because that's why we are trying to save her.
We have to do whatever we can to keep her safe and healthy.
That's my role here, being Mandi's mum.
In the wild, baby tapirs are camouflaged with stripes until around three months old and they're reliant on their mothers for milk and protection.
Mandi is five months old, how do you think she's doing now?
She's doing very well.
She's now acting more like a tapir instead of being, you know, close to humans and begging for human company.
Now, she's more independent, she's doing very well.
And with her new-found confidence, Mandi is starting to become a bit of a handful.
As if on cue!
It's interesting seeing Mandi who, you know, seemed like a very relaxed creature... ..but now she's getting a lot more active.
That milk's finished and she wants to play.
And her method of playing is head-butting, which actually can be quite painful considering how big she is.
'Baby tapirs use playtime to learn survival skills.
'It's not just humans that want to eat them.
'In the wild, they have to avoid being eaten by predators.'
Now, as much as she is the largest land mammal in Central America and South America, she does have predators and one of those predators is a jaguar.
Now, there are several things that tapirs have to their advantage.
One is their massive size and also they have a thick hide, especially around the neck.
That is where the jaguar is going to try and target.
So, all this activity, all this play, is really important for her to learn how to be a wild tapir.
'This defensive play also signals that Mandi is ready 'for the next stage in her rehabilitation.
She's showing us who's boss, that's for sure.
Yeah.
I'm trying to stay light on my feet right now.
'Rodolfo's plan is to introduce her gradually 'to two other rescued tapirs in the sanctuary.
'The challenge for Mandi now is to be accepted by her own kind.'
Over 7,500 miles away, I'm in South Africa 'helping Manji, the baby rhino.'
This intensive care unit has been instrumental in helping Manji overcome the trauma of his past, but it's time for him to move on and discover the world beyond these four walls.
Petronel's sanctuary is set in nearly 5,000 hectares of African bushveld.
And Manji is moving to a purpose-built enclosure known as a boma.
But he won't be moving alone.
Since arriving here, he's formed a very strong bond with two other rhinos who, like him, had a traumatic start in life.
Mia and Venus.
Do you want to pick me up?
Petronel has spent so much time nursing and caring for this trio, she knows all their character traits.
If you look at the personalities just in this camp here, you could clearly see who is the cheeky one and the feisty one and that's Venus.
She will protect these guys and be a real matriarch, you know, a real leader.
Mia is just such a softie, enjoy to be touched, very affectionate, where Manji, look at him playing there, brilliant boy, inquisitive.
Not too bothered about what the girls are up to at all.
Their new home is over 1km away and is ten times larger than their old one.
It's situated on the edge of the wild reserve, where a herd of rhinos roam free.
Petronel's dream is that Manji will soon join them.
She has designed every element of the boma and is making a final check to ensure everything is in order.
A last inspection.
Now, that's good.
And then one in that corner.
With experience and other animals, you can put them through the rehabilitation process so much quicker.
So, for me it's quite important to make sure that this boma and their new home will be the best for them ever.
It's like a palace, it's like a castle for a king, you know, and that's what I want for them.
I think they will enjoy this immensely.
Manji and his herd, Venus and Mia, have all had traumatic pasts, so Petronel wants to make this journey as easy as possible.
Having years of experience moving rhinos, her plan is to transport them across the sanctuary while they are under sedation.
Jump, jump, jump, jump, jump.
Jump, jump.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
See here.
Now, our pulse ox is working, thank you.
We're just making sure all the equipment is working fine.
You don't want to stand here and then the equipment is not doing what they're supposed to do.
Giving anaesthetic to one young animal is worrying, but immobilising all three of them comes with even greater risks.
Ja, it's a big day.
Sitting with this headache just over my eyes here and it only lift when the animals are awake and happy and doing well and breathing fine again.
With preparation complete, Manji is the first of his herd to be moved.
And wildlife vet Dr Ferreira uses a pole syringe to inject him with a sedative.
He's very used to be with Venus and Mia, so I can see it in his eyes as well the chemical... start working as well.
Petronel uses a blindfold and earplugs to reduce the stress.
While he's under sedation, there's one other routine job to do.
Rhino horn is made of keratin, a protein composed of dead cells, like human hair and nails.
With no nerves or feeling in it, Petronel believes that keeping it short is a painless and vital way to stop Manji being poached.
I don't want to put Manji's life in danger, so if they go out to the wild where everyone want them and they have their horn on, they're going to be killed.
They are going to be poached and we will find more carcasses.
So if we can protect them, let's do everything in our power to protect them.
Rhino horn is highly sought-after on the international black market, to be used in traditional Chinese medicine.
It's the main reason that rhinos are killed in the wild.
You see.
One, two, three.
Come to the front.
With his horn trimmed, the team are confident that they have taken every precaution to protect him and he is on his way across the sanctuary to his new home.
The vet team reverse the effects of the anaesthetic and Manji gets up quickly.
You can clearly hear him sniffing.
Smelling everything in the new house.
It looks like it smells very nice.
This is so great.
We're going to get Venus now, ja, ja.
And then the two of you can discuss this crazy new house.
The preparation for Venus is a little bit different.
We need everyone away and it must be very quiet with Venus.
She's a complete different animal than Manji.
If she picks up on any movement, her adrenaline is going to kick in and then we won't be able to work with her at all.
If Venus becomes too stressed, the anaesthetic won't be as effective and she could injure herself or the team.
But with patience and the right conditions, Venus eventually goes to sleep.
And with her horn trimmed, she too is ready to be taken to her new home.
Mia gets the same treatment and is not far behind.
It's an amazing feeling.
Look at this.
S Reunited, the herd begin to enjoy the boma's design features.
Already eating, already very interested, this is their new Jacuzzi mud bath.
A mud bath is not something that Manji has ever experienced.
And he isn't quite sure what to make of it.
Manji doesn't know what this is.
So, we have to definitely try and teach Manji the enjoyment of the water and the mud.
He's actually at the moment hiding away a little bit and scratching himself against the tyre.
And that, for him, is what he knows.
But herd leader Venus is keen to give the Jacuzzi mud bath a try.
Oh-ooh, dis so lekker.
Ohhh-ohhh-ohh.
I can't tell you, the relief is amazing for me, the relief is just something else.
She wants to play.
Following Venus' lead, Manji takes the plunge too.
Ohh, there we go.
This is Manji's first ever proper mud bath.
Could never do it, the wound on his face and the previous area was just not suitable for this at all.
In some places, rhino skin is nearly 100 times thicker than human skin, but they can still suffer from insect bites and sunburn.
Wallowing in mud helps protect them.
And seeing them enjoy it is a happy bonus for Petronel.
I once asked myself, "What will happen if you have to give your life?"
And moments like this make that decision easy.
The world would be such a...such a sad place without these creatures.
I will give my life to these guys in a blink.
But Petronel will soon have less contact with Manji.
She hopes to release him into her reserve - 5,000 hectares of African bush - where he'll live alongside the wild rhino herd.
But before that can happen, Manji needs to learn how to find food for himself.
And learning to graze in the outside area of the boma, will be the next step of his rehabilitation.
Over in Costa Rica, Mandi the orphaned tapir is making good progress too.
HE WHISTLES As well as looking after her, Rodolfo is also responsible for over 600 other animals.
And they certainly know how to keep him on his toes.
This is a spider monkey.
Sometimes they find a way to escape from the enclosure, they're very smart animals.
To help with their development, Rodolfo likes to put animals of their own kind together.
But sometimes this isn't possible and he ends up providing hands-on care.
Sometimes I have to be a tapir, sometimes I have to be a cat.
This is Gatita, she's a margay, a type of wild cat.
She was rescued and brought to the centre when she was just three weeks old.
Now over six months old, she's playing a little rough.
GATITA MEOWS She was like half of the size, she was just a little, little kitten.
It's amazing to see how she's improving, you know, growing very strong, playful and active all the time.
Rodolfo is not the only one helping with her development.
Gatita has found an unlikely friend in his rescue dog, Perrillo.
Margay's are expert jungle climbers... ..and at this age, use play to practise their hunting skills.
She's doing great.
I would like, in the future, to see her being in the wild for good, you know, forever.
Gatita will return to the wild when she's old enough.
But Rodolfo's biggest challenge is keeping on top of Mandi's development, and she's ready to take the next step.
Every day, he takes her out for a walk.
Let's go, Mandi.
And there's one place she finds irresistible.
They have a very good sense of smell and she knows that there are other tapirs here.
The idea here is to introduce Mandi with them.
Bribri is a seven-year-old tapir who came to the sanctuary after being rescued from hunters... ..and she has a son, three-month-old Bubu.
Mandi's curiosity is a clear indication to Rodolfo that she'd like to have contact with other tapirs.
You know, she forget completely about me and then she's just looking, smelling around to see if she can find her own mum, but she's not here.
Mandi might be keen to get to know them, but the feeling isn't mutual.
Mother Bribri is very protective of her son Bubu.
Now Mandi is trying to get some contact with the mother.
And Rodolfo thinks she sees Mandi as a threat.
The mother is mad.
Bribri has a muscular jaw and a powerful bite.
Her well-developed, chisel-like teeth could seriously injure a predator like a jaguar.
So, even through the fence, Bribri could injure Mandi.
She's not very happy and then she's just trying to attack anything that moves, including Mandi.
Mandi is unable to read the situation and is unaware of the danger she's facing.
This is really frustrating for me, you know, because every time that Mandi comes here, that's what she get, rejection.
You know.
And then she's just looking...begging for...for a mum, that's a normal behaviour.
This is a set-back for Mandi.
And for now, she's going back to the safety of her own enclosure.
Mandi.
It's really quite heartbreaking to know that Mandi is so close to getting the attention she needs, but if Mandi's going to be accepted, then she needs to start acting like a tapir.
But lucky enough her, she has Rodolfo to give her a head start.
Rodolfo's plan is to put Mandi through some serious jungle training.
If she can start honing her wild tapir skills, she'll have a much better chance of being accepted by Bribri and Bubu.
In Africa, Manji the baby rhino has already been accepted by his herd, Venus and Mia.
Now settled into their new home, surrogate mum Petronel wants to make sure they continue in their development.
Manji didn't get enough time with his mum to learn all the skills of how to be a rhino, even something simple like knowing how to graze grass and use those lips is completely foreign to him.
And that is going to be his next challenge.
White rhinos have a square mouth with wide, prehensile lips that can grab, enabling them to graze and eat grass more efficiently than a lawnmower.
Until now, Manji's only eaten prepared, cut grass and has never had the opportunity to find his own food.
With moral support from his herd, he's going to venture into the outside area of the boma.
And it's a key part of Petronel's strategy.
I've learned through years of experience - give them their space and give them time, don't try and rush them.
Don't try and let them do the things you want them to do.
We don't want prisoners, we want wild animals.
Rhinos are incredibly sensitive and Petronel isn't sure how Manji will react.
Another big day for Manji.
Now he's going to come out and really smell and see natural-growing veld and grass for the first time.
And his natural instinct will come out of grazing and he will definitely follow Venus' lead.
So, let's see what they do.
Hello.
Kom, kom.
There...there's Manji first coming and...
But Manji doesn't remember a world outside of an enclosure and lets Venus and Mia take the first steps.
There we go.
Kom, kom.
SHE GASPS It's OK, it's OK.
This is the largest open space they've been in since they lost their mothers and their natural instincts kick in.
Bit too much for Venus, you can see that clearly.
A big step.
Going back to their safe place.
It's overwhelming and they all head back inside.
It's wonderful, but also a little bit of our first day at school type of situation.
But with encouragement, they give it another go.
There we go.
Kom, kom, kom.
Rhinos rely heavily on their well-developed sense of smell and they use it in the wild to detect other animals from over a quarter of a mile away.
This is a big, big, big step for them.
This new space is packed full of new smells, and the unfamiliar triggers a defensive instinct.
The way they're standing is also protecting each other.
Very good behaviour for rhino.
And there's Manji and Venus following me now.
Manji's staying with Venus and they will just carry along and come more out and more out and test the waters more and more and more.
With herd leader Venus at ease, Manji and Mia relax too.
It's like a herd.
Wow.
It looks like they have been doing this forever.
For me, that's so amazing, you know?
They've been through hell.
It's the first time, now, that they can be out in the open, and...it's good, it's...it's grazing and herd behaviour.
It's good to see them like this - the way a white rhino must graze.
And there's Manji, also trying.
Manji needs to learn to... pluck the grass with his lips.
So, I think he will have to learn to do that.
At two months old, a rhino calf will start to graze on a range of vegetation, and Petronel knows how important this milestone is.
I want them so badly out here and grazing, and it's a privilege for me to see this today, and just to be part of the herd.
And them coming and going and being free - it's just the best day ever.
Manji is on course with his rehabilitation, and if all goes to plan, his next step will be freedom into the wild reserve.
In Costa Rica, Mandi the tapir is also about to learn survival skills.
Hey, Mandi.
Drink.
To bring her closer to tapirs Bribri and Bubu, Rodolfo wants Mandi to develop more of the jungle traits essential to being a tapir.
In the wild, tapirs will spend up to two years with their mothers.
And you can see that little Bubu is watching his mother Bribri very carefully, everything that she does.
And he can see that she's eating these bananas, and...
There you go.
This is the first time that he's eating bananas, and he's learnt that from his mum.
He's watched her, he's seen that it's safe to eat, and he's copied her, and this is something that Mandi's missing out on.
Without her own kind to be with...
..Rodolfo has assumed the role of surrogate mum and is taking Mandi on a walk with a purpose.
Today I am taking Mandi to the forest, giving her the opportunity to learn.
At this age, baby tapirs would be chaperoned for protection.
And Rodolfo is on hand to help Mandi learn how to stay safe in the forest.
It takes time and a lot of patience.
She has to learn to act like a tapir, and then that's why I'm here, for that.
Right now she's eating a tree called guasimo.
This tree's all over this area - it's a native tree.
Oh, my God.
I'm so proud of Mandi.
Good girl, Mandi.
But forest walks are not just about foraging.
In the wild, if a tapir feels threatened, they seek safety in water.
That was a normal reaction.
They have to be always with their signs active, and she just heard something, and she just jump.
But water plays another role for tapir safety.
This is a vital lesson for Mandi, but a less glamorous one for her teacher.
I'm trying to get Mandi poo, and then I just spray water on her body.
Oh.
Almost, Mandi.
See?
She poo!
Finally.
Look at that.
You can see those bubbles.
Oh, look at this.
This is what...this is what we are waiting for.
This is very good news.
This is why I bring her here.
She needs to use the river as a bathroom, and that's the idea - they have to hide their smell from the jaguars.
They also have another strategy to escape jaguars.
They are excellent divers and are agile underwater.
And they can even hold their breath for several minutes.
Now she's relaxed because she poo, and then now it's time to play.
I have to be very careful with her bites.
If they can't reach water, tapirs might need to defend themselves, and it's important that Mandi practises using her strength.
She's trying to push me into the water.
These trips into the forest will continue until Mandi is ready for her next step, which is to meet Bubu, the other baby tapir that lives at the sanctuary.
'Over in South Africa, 'Manji and his herd have now settled into 'a routine of grazing for themselves.
'And that means they are now ready to be released 'and to live with the wild herd.
'But Manji is not the only animal 'that Petronel is busy rehabilitating.
'I'm about to feed two other orphans.
'20-month-old hippo Emma...'
She responds to her name.
Ja.
She's a very clever lady.
'..And rescued six-month-old baby Molly.'
Look at this little thing.
Oh, my word.
'Molly's favourite food is this vegetables smoothie.'
This is...this is quite something, to be this close to hippopotamuses, because they have a reputation for being extremely fearsome, so...can't quite believe I'm doing this.
They're known as the deadliest mammals in Africa, but Emma, after escaping poachers at a young age, has been hand-raised by Petronel, and they still have a close bond.
Emma seems to be quite imprinted and tame, right?
I mean, it's not normal to be able to get that close to a hippo.
Will she end up in the wild as well?
A way of rehabilitation that's quite important for me is you have to know when you need to step back.
Sometimes you're in the way of the rehabilitation process and the release process.
Sometimes we, as humans, keep that connection and that bond, but that's a selfish bond for us.
What will be good for her is for me to step out of the way.
Baby Molly came here after her mother was shot.
Left defenceless, Molly was attacked by bushpigs.
Petronel has been treating her scars with moisturiser ever since.
This is a very surreal experience - rubbing cream on a baby hippo.
The scars on the outside was nothing.
Emotionally, this animal was really nowhere.
Has pairing Molly with Emma helped in her rehabilitation?
Absolutely.
I don't think I would've been able to save Molly without Emma.
Molly refused to drink, she refused to eat, she refused to react.
You could see there's nothing to work with.
She was in such a condition that there was no trust.
So Emma became a surrogate mum for Molly...
Absolutely.
..And the two have become inseparable ever since, I'm guessing.
Ja.
But Molly's moisturiser is not on the menu.
She's eating the cream!
You can't eat that!
Naughty girl!
PETRONEL GIGGLES No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
So, what's the next stage for these guys?
We're busy preparing an area for them near the river with much less human contact, and take Molly and basically wean her completely off human food and let them graze.
For me, I can't wait to see them in the river.
Yeah.
Emma and Molly are proof that creating strong bonds between orphans is a successful way to rehabilitate wildlife.
But with herd animals, if one of the group is suffering from trauma, that can hold up the future rehabilitation of the whole herd.
'Today, Venus needs a medical examination, 'and the results could put the brakes on 'tomorrow's planned release for Manji.'
Of course, it's important that all of Manji's herd are in tiptop condition for them to make it to the next level.
Venus has a sore foot.
A lingering injury from when she was rescued from the poachers.
Petronel has helped the wounds to heal... ..but Venus still occasionally limps, and so needs an X-ray to determine if there is an underlying medical problem.
We have one here under the seat, so...
So, we've brought all the medical equipment we need down here to the boma because when you're dealing with an animal the size of a rhino, the hospital has to come to the patient.
A good result from this morning's test is vital, not just for Venus, but for Manji too.
If we want to let them go, and she starts limping or there's infection starting in that foot again, I will have to bring the whole group back again.
This would mean a big backwards step in their rehabilitation.
This way.
This way, big girl.
Venus is given a sedative, and Manji and Mia are led into the boma next door.
Rhinos' feet have three toes that surround a soft elastic sole.
This design is crucial to help balance their body weight evenly.
I mean, you think about this, an animal this size, a rhino, and it's carrying this enormous weight on these four tiny points.
For it to have a problem with its foot, a sore foot, it's going to make it lame really quickly, so it is really important that this gets fixed.
To get to the root of the problem, we're going to use a mobile X-ray machine.
So, I've got on a protective suit.
The resulting image will hopefully show the vet team why Venus is still experiencing pain.
It is amazing what you can do today, that you can bring this kind of equipment and do this kind of a procedure in the field.
The vets process the images, and Petronel is apprehensive about the diagnosis.
I'm just waiting for the results to see, but without that visible wound, there was nothing - this was all just wound.
Why is she sometimes limping and other times not limping?
Is there something that we maybe missed?
'The results are in...'
We're concerned that there might be a bone infection.
Erm... '..and it's not the good news they were hoping for.'
It's a bit...
Yeah, it's...
It's not as clear.
It's eroded, isn't it?
Yeah, it's eroded.
So, we've just found out that it looks like Venus has got infections in her bones in her foot, which is a lot more of a serious problem.
Because she had such an incredibly large wound, the whole of her underside, that that's actually spread into the bones.
Yeah.
..That's my concern.
Right.
How do you feel, Petronel?
I know, you know?
My gut was telling me that there was something wrong.
I wish I could see her running again, so what lies ahead, we will just blow through there, and we will make sure that she's fine.
Let's make sure that she can run again.
Fortunately, the vet team have got what they think will be a solution.
They decide to administer an antibiotic that will boost Venus' immune system which will fight the infection.
While we have her under sedation, that's the last treatment, and it will penetrate.
We concentrate the antibiotic in that spot.
The team will also be able to keep an eye on her when she's in the wild reserve to ensure she's healing properly.
The effects of the sedation are reversed, and she is up and back to her normal self in no time.
Hey, Manji.
How are you doing?
'And Manji is reunited with his best friend.'
Can you see this?
Mm.
He's just comforting her.
I know.
Isn't that sweet?
Manji's comforting Venus.
It's so sweet.
Is Venus still on course to return with this herd into the next stage of her rehabilitation?
We're going to fit the treatments in.
I think it will be good for her if we not focus on that and we focus on the positive.
And I know by separating her and Manji, that's not going to help the process.
Mm.
They have to stick together.
This group will stick together in the next step.
Now Manji is the stronger one, Mia's a very strong one, and they will just pull Venus through.
So, no, they will be released.
That's just incredibly touching, to see the...tenderness between these rhinos.
The bonds that they have with each other, they are...they're really strong, and that togetherness and those bonds are clearly so important in their healing process.
Tomorrow Manji and the whole of his herd will reach the final stage of their rehabilitation.
Over in Costa Rica, Mandi the tapir is about to take a huge leap forward in her rehabilitation.
She's now learned enough wild behaviours to start the bonding process with another tapir, and Rodolfo wants to introduce her to baby Bubu.
Today is a very, very big day for Mandi because we're going to introduce her with the other baby tapir we have we have here in the sanctuary.
In order for Bubu to have a chance to make friends with Mandi, they temporarily put Mum, Bribri, in a nearby enclosure.
This is the first time Bubu has met another tapir too, and Rodolfo wants their encounter to go well.
The worst situation here is that he attack her suddenly.
You know, he's still a baby, he just know how to behave with his mum, but we really need Mandi being close to him for the future plans.
Rodolfo hopes Mandi will start a family in the future and thinks Bubu could be a perfect match.
Tapirs aren't able to breed until they're at least a year old, but with the species under threat, Rodolfo is planning ahead.
This situation make me feel very excited because if we have a positive result, oh, my God, that's what we are looking for, you know?
That would be very awesome.
Mandi is keen to get out on her daily walk...
..But going into Bubu's enclosure is new to her.
Mandi's just exploring, trying to see if the place is safe for her.
They haven't met yet, but suddenly something can happen.
Now she wants to swim in the same pool where the baby and the mummy was - she's trying to get inside.
Just like being in the river, the water pool makes Mandi feel safe.
Uh-oh!
He's coming.
Hey, big guy.
Who is the girl?
I want you to introduce Mandi.
Come.
This is a very important step for Mandi, a big, big step, because this is the first time she meets another tapir since her mother was killed.
And it's their love of bananas that brings them closer together.
Yes.
Oh, my God.
Mandi.
This interaction might be fleeting, but for Rodolfo it's a great start.
This is a really good moment for Mandi because since now the idea is to continue doing this exercise.
The situation here is that Mandi's having so much fun that I don't know how to take her out.
Rodolfo just about managed to persuade Mandi to leave her new friend.
Rodolfo, tell me, what's the future for Mandi here?
What's the next step?
Well, the idea is that she might have babies with Bubu, and then we can have the chance to release their offspring back to the wild - that's the main purpose here.
And how does that make you feel, knowing that she's undergone this huge journey from being tied up, battered and bruised to hopefully becoming a mother?
Oh, that is a very nice feeling.
It's something really amazing, to have the opportunity, me, as a human, to work with a tapir.
After all that she passed through, seeing Mandi acting like a tapir and finally having her own babies, that would be a very special moment, definitely.
Well, good luck, Mandi.
It's a long road ahead for Mandi, but thanks to the dedicated work of Rodolfo, the future looks brighter for her, and hopefully, the survival of her species.
It's early morning... ..and it's a huge day ahead for Manji, Venus and Mia.
They're going to be released into a wild area that is 5,000 hectares.
This protected wilderness is home to seven other rehabilitated rhinos, and Manji will finally get the chance to be part of a wild herd.
Do you think they've outgrown this boma and it's time for Manji and his herd to bust out into the wilder area?
Absolutely.
You know, they're kicking out of the nest a bit.
You know, "Mum, we're ready to fly."
They're ready.
And definitely, you know, they're telling me, you know, that it's time.
And how do you think Manji's going to react to this new wilder area and these new rhinos?
Mia is the strong one in this group, so I think she will show the way, but let's see their personality, what's going to happen.
But I think Manji can't do it.
I think he will, at one stage, hang back and see what the big girls will do, and then he will say, "Ah, that's OK.
Let's do this."
White rhinos are incredibly social, and a wild herd can contain up to 14 individuals.
This moment has been Petronel's dream from the very beginning.
How do you feel about losing your baby boy?
Erm...
I think it will hit me at a stage.
I...
You know, I prepare psychological for days like this, you know?
And I don't want him to get hurt.
I think he went through enough, you know?
I want it to go smooth.
It's like bike riding, you know?
At one stage, Mum is not there, you know, but Mum is also feeling...
"I hope he doesn't fall," you know?
So, yeah, mixed feelings.
Manji, are you lying in the way?
Hey!
Hey, my boy.
'Before they're released, 'Petronel wants to make sure they feel as self-assured as possible...'
Come, come, come.
'..And knows exactly how to achieve the right frame of mind.'
Is this a fun treat for them, a mud bath?
It's such a treat.
It's such an amazing treat for rhinos, and before we take them out, I would love them just to have a relaxed time a little bit and get their mood...set the mood for what must happen, you know?
Right.
And convince them that it's good, ja?
It's a mud bath confidence booster.
PETRONEL LAUGHS They go just all silly in it, don't they?
Yeah.
They just, like...
It's like they're in a silly mood.
The atmosphere changes as soon as this water's presented to them, and they just...they turn into silly rhinos.
The Jacuzzi mud bath does the trick, and Manji and his herd are soon in high spirits.
Woo!
They're getting playful.
It's slightly unnerving, if I'm honest... ..cos these are big guys, but it's joyous.
This display of confidence is proof to Petronel that Manji is ready.
The last time he saw a big rhino was when his mum died.
I think it will be a little bit stressful, there will be a little bit of trauma involved, and then as soon as he sees...
"Oh, but they're settling down.
They're eating, "they're greeting us in a good way.
"I belong here!
This is my home.
"Wow!
I love this."
The time has come to walk Manji and his herd out of the boma.
Manji!
Kom, kom!
Kom, julle!
Come on.
Come on, Manji.
'They're so excited, we don't have time to open the gate.'
'With their exit blocked... 'they turn around 'and suddenly, over a tonne of rhinos are heading straight for us.'
Quick, quick, quick, quick, quick.
This open.
Kom, kom, kom, kom, kom, kom!
Mia is the first to be free.
And Manji and Venus are not far behind.
Look at that.
Running into the new area.
Look at these guys!
They are ready to be wild rhinos.
Amazing!
None of us expected that.
They wanted to do this!
I know.
They were jumping for joy.
They were just like...
Look at them, look at them.
Yeah.
PETRONEL LAUGHS It's just...
This is amazing.
It feels really emotional, actually, to see them just, like, run like that.
It's really hugely exciting.
Oh, yeah, I love it, I love it.
Look at that beautiful gallop.
Oh, it's absolutely astonishing.
I mean, that is not an animal that is traumatised, antisocial.
You know, that's...that, for all intents and purposes, he's a wild rhino right now, isn't he?
Now they're meeting the group.
Have a look here.
Come have a look here.
Oh!
So, how many are there in there?
Ten now.
Ten?
Ten.
Wow!
So, it's a proper size wild herd, isn't it?
Not a baby.
THEY CHUCKLE Yeah, I'm a happy mum.
This new group instinctively begin to bond as a herd, and Manji has finally made it back to where he belongs.
It's as if they've been together forever.
They're, like, moving as one, like a big rhino river.
And Manji's right in the thick of it, right in the middle of his new herd.
Petronel, I have to say, I don't think I've ever met anybody that works as hard as you.
I just...
It's amazing the dedication that you put in to saving his animals.
Sometimes, like, yesterday, I didn't feel well about...
..Venus, but now, looking at her...that's good.
Aw!
That's good.
So great.
So amazing what you've done.
This species, the survival of this species is what we want to accomplish, and now, if these guys together and the stress of human contact is out, I think they'll breed.
In the years to come, they will definitely breed, yeah.
We must just protect them.
You're going to be a grandmother.
PETRONEL LAUGHS Yes, we can!
You and I, we're going to change this country.
Let's go get 'em.
You run, and hopefully win, elected office not just for the sake of being something, but for the sake of doing something.
I knew that seven presidents had tried, seven presidents had failed.
He said, "I am President of the United States, "and I can't make anything happen."
A BBC Two exclusive with the president and his team...